[Music]
now I must say a number of technical
things so
conventions here we have to appeal to
linear algebra so please follow us I'll
describe everything in exact details but
it will be Technical and just to try to
absolve as much as you can and I'll show
you some examples to explain and to
clarify what I mean by those
technicalities we have a
manifold M and let's say that this man
fold is oriented oriented locally
by a basis of tangent
[Applause]
vectors call them E1 and so on through e
m so small m is the dimension of the
manifold and a
map F which goes from M to M there are
several objects that we'd like to
consider
and we want to put orientations on of
them first object is the
[Applause]
diagonal what do we mean by the
diagonal when you have a manifold which
should denote this diagonal by Capital
Delta of M do you know this lettera so
it's called Delta you might have seen
the lower case Delta but this is the
capital Delta and this is
simply
a set of this typee in other words if
you have M and M Delta is exactly
diagonal is exactly I shall draw it with
u with yellow and
zero that's Delta
of okay all the points on Delta have
equal components XY components if you
like Okay so 45° so the standed thing is
Delta but please remember that this is
an abstract picture it works in any
Dimension okay so if you have a 100
dimensional space you can take the
diagonal which lives in 100 + 10000
dimensional direct product and this
diagonal is what we're talking about
okay so this um is oriented
by so I'm going to complement the
sentence before given the manifold
oriented locally by these vectors and
the map we shall
Orient the
diagonal by the following
vectors E1
E1 through e m e m what do we mean by
this what's this E1 E1 well this is a
vector so it has some components you
know components that Vector has length
M because we're in m m dimensional
space I just copy the same components
underneath and make a longer Vector of
Dimension 2 m that's what I mean here
and that makes sense because you see if
M has say an orienting Vector which is
like this here also there's an orienting
vector and what is the vector which
points along M well it's the vector
whose horizontal and vertical components
are exactly the
same for example if you have a vector 1
Z this is 01 well what's the vector
pointing along the diagonal it's the
vector 1 one so it's the same thing
similarly 22 will point along the
diagonal 3 three - one - one so so you
should have the same copies of the
components here and here okay so that's
how we oriented diagonal there are M
vectors and that's going to be the basis
ref spaces that tells you with respect
to this you have positive negative
orientation okay
next the graph of
the this part as I said is technical so
please bear with
us
but we have to say this in order
to use the intersection Theory with its
full power so that we can compute things
next the graph I don't mean the graph in
the sense of graph Theory but graph in
the sense of elementary mathematics so
this is the we shall call it the gamma
of capital gamma of F and it is simply a
subset of the
product of the
form
yeah again easy to see what it is in
pictures sorry that's M that's
M graph might be something like this so
that's gamma of
f okay and this gamma of f we shall um
Orient
you see the sentence structure we Orient
diagonal by this the graph by
defa
E1 so you put the vector there and then
underneath we shall put the derivative
of
f applied to
E1 and then so on and then e m
derivative of f appli to
em why is
this look at this picture again and
let's take for example this
point suppose that we have a
vector which is pointing this way with
length
two I ask you what is the vector which
is tangent to this graph and which is
tilted like this what are the components
of this Vector well the horizontal
component is two and what's the vertical
component it's the derivative at this
point times
two is that
clear it's not if it's not that means
that you did not learn
calculus the slope is simply equal to
this over
this so if the slope is derivative if
this is two this is derivative time two
if this three it's D * 3 if it's -1 this
is derivative *
-1
okay so the vertical and horizontal
components are if this is E1 this is
derivative applied to
E1 okay so that's why we take those
vectors and those all those vectors M
vectors each one has length to M are
tangent to and Define the bases
orienting bases for the graph at each
point
okay so that's the orientation of the
graph and finally there's a third thing
that we have to
orient which is M cross M this is the
simplest one by the following
vectors even1
zero this is a
vector of length zero or length
M all entri
is
zero
and then e m to zero and then we have to
have some others 0
E1 and
Z how many vectors are there now there
are two M vectors that makes sense
because the dimension of M CR m is not M
but 2 m and that's what we shall take as
the orienting
basis okay
the all these um statements makes sense
dimensionally because note
that the dimension of the diagonal of
this manifold is equal to the dimension
of the graph of this which is equal to
the dimension of the manifold itself and
it is equal to m in this case small M
and also the dimension of
the ambient stage if you like the
ambient space m CR m is of course twice
that Dimension 2
m we notice immediately that the
dimension of the
diagonal plus the dimension of the
graph equals the dimension of the
ambient space so the Overflow is
zero that means that we can start
talking about intersection
numbers graph and the diagonal intersect
discrete points we can count whether the
sign is plus or minus thanks to these
orientations count the intersection
number and use the powerful Machinery of
intersection Theory to dce all sorts of
conclusions about the
map
so we can
play intersection
Theory
with the diagonal and Gamma graph
inside M cross
M and indeed that was a
motivation when you look at this picture
the fixed points which correspond to
roots of the equation are exactly where
the graph and the diagonal intersect
those are the points that we would like
to detect and we also would like to know
whether there are such points which
corresponds to the equation are there
roots of the
equation
okay
good now as I said this description
accurate and complete though it was was
rather technical let's look at what
should we look at an
example to know how to
do this in
practice and here I'll will be
asking questions so please don't be
shy an important example then in order
to understand what all these things mean
in
practice consider a
map that goes from R2 to R
R2 a map of of the pl itself and we
shall say that this map sends the point
XY to the point x^2 - y^2 /
2 x
y okay that's a certain map for example
the origin goes to the origin as you can
see and many other points
okay do you recognize this map have you
seen it
before
no I can no longer trust this silence as
meaning no because a moment ago I asked
have you seen the Jordan and he was
silent I thought he was no but you know
clever people like taboka started saying
oh yes yes I have seen it 30 seconds
later so have you seen this
before yes you have but in
Disguise consider the complex number
representation z = x + y if I take the
square of this and divide by two the
real part is x^2 - y^ 2/ 2 the imaginary
part is XY so that's what it is so the
map is in fact in complex number
representation Z goes to Z 2 / two
that's what this map is okay I hope then
that you can picture visualize what this
map does can you do you know what it
means in complex numbers to
multiply in particular do you know what
it means to take the square of a complex
number do you have a geometry of this I
hope you do if you don't you keeping
silent you should come see me after
class and we'll revise that it's a very
very fundamental thing
okay so that's the map that we shall
consider
now I I have to ask you what is the
derivative of this
map how do you calculate the derivative
of this map do you
know it's a map from two Dimension to
two Dimension if you have a map a
function from 1D to 1D all of us have
been calculating derivatives for many
many years but what's the derivative of
such a thing any idea component compon
component wise okay so what is the
derivative going to be is it going to
become a
vector is it going to become a
scalar is it going to become something
else thre what do you think it's going
to
become what's the
map what's the
derivative have you ever heard of the
Jacobian yes you have not somebody says
yes who said
yes mon says
yes so what do we
do the derivative of this is a
combination of partial derivatives and
it's not a vector it's a
matrix we should remember this because
this is really
fundamental it's the first thing that we
learned in calculus multivariable
calculus and it's the last thing we
should forget
because after all you recognize the
importance of derivative what do we mean
by derivative if you think that the
world you living is onedimensional
then fine just to remember the what the
derivative is in one D but do you live
in the one dimensional world no I hope
not I personally live in a higher
dimensional
space so I want to have the concept of
derivative well understood in all
Dimensions so what it does is the f
you take this component and you take the
partial derivative with respect to the
first variable so you get this number
here here you get the same component but
you take the derivative with respect to
the other variable and you can now guess
what the other two entries are it is
this and it is
this I like ask have you ever come
across anything like this in your
life
huh somewhere before well this is what
the derivative of a multivariable higher
dimensional function looks like I hope
you can understand the pattern okay so
let's calculate this what are these well
it's easy right derivative x - y YX
that's what it
is do you recognize what this is if
you're thinking in terms of bless you
for complex numbers this should become
quite
clear
okay and
that's called
the Jacobian by most speakers of English
and French but in fact Mr yobi was a
German Jew of German origin so it should
be called yoban not
Jacobian
good well that's the derivative let's
look at the
orientations um we shall
Orient let's define two vectors that
Orient R2 okay they don't have to be 1 0
01 any two linear independent vectors
will do so I'm going to write down 1 two
and 3 4 are these linearly independent
yes they are they are not parallel to
each other so they're impendent so if
these two vectors have been chosen to
orient r
two
then we shall start
orienting the diagonal the graph and the
product the
diagonal is oriented by what kind of
vectors let's look at
this that's E1 that's E2 so what's the
first Vector of the orienting basis for
the
diagonal one two and then
what one two one two thank you very much
who said that TR said that or somebody
okay and then what's the next
Vector
huh Sarah you have an
idea huh 3 3 4 34 exactly so that's
what this means okay so that's going to
be the orientation there are two vectors
this is two dimensional and that's the
basis so if you take another basis you
can decide whether the basis you have
taken is positive or negative the same
orientation or the orientation with
respect to these okay next what
about the
graph
the graph of
f so that's the orienting
basis what are the vectors that we have
to
take now
T what's the vector you have to take the
first first
Vector what do you have
here yeah yeah you can you can see that
right so it's one two here because
that's the first
Vector is that
clear and then what you have to do it
says derivatives of f applied on E1 that
is you have to apply this Matrix to one
two is that clear
okay so what I have to do let me write
it in detail so x - y YX can you see
this from that distance applied on one
two that's the first Vector it's going
to have size
four okay what is this it's one two if I
do the Matrix modifcation I hope
everyone can it is x - 2 y yes and Y -
2x
huh plus 2 good okay and then the what's
the next Vector it's 34 and then again x
- y y x apply them 34 and if I do the
calculation it's 3 4 3x - 4 Y and then 3
y + 4x okay so those are
the vectors okay good
for
example what do I mean by those num
symbols X and Y for example let's say
that you want to have the orienting
basis at a certain
point at the
point XY let's say that we take the
point
56 what I'm doing is simply the
following look at that picture of gra
again you see the orientation Vector was
basis at this point is this one but if I
go here it's this one if I go here it's
this one and so on you see the vector
changes the basis changes so at some
point x I have a certain Vector another
point x I have some other vector and so
forth that's why you have this
dependence on X and Y depending on where
you are so so let's calculate what the
um orientation vectors are at the
56 well it's easy all you have to do is
to plug in five and six into those
numbers so it's 1 2 now what is this 5
minus 12 what's
this - 7 I think and then 6 + 10 16
that's nice and then what's this 3 4
3x - 4 y what's
that the first person who answers gets
an ice cream minus 9 I was
first you have to be quick is this even
correct and then the next one is 38
apparently okay so that's what it is
okay you understand and finally what's
the orientation basis for M cross M
product
that's the easiest
one say this so for
example is that his name I think
so
hi what are the orientation vectors for
M cross
n m this is in fact
R2 and
R2 so maybe we should have written that
small instru this this is diagonal of
inside R2 Okay now what's the
orientation Vector according to this
recipe we have to take those
vectors okay how many vectors would I
get at the
end say
this huh * 2 what * 2 2 * 2 what's 2 * 2
four four okay four vector and what are
the components of the vectors
please the first Vector what's
that look at
that 1 120 0 that's correct and the
second
one 3 40 thank you very much and the
third one no 0 1 2 0 012 okay we have
understood everything so and then the
fourth one is of course 0 0 3 4 okay so
those are the Orting vectors of and the
question is
whether the intersection of the diagonal
and the graph is positive or negative
inside this product so we have to figure
out whether the joint orientation of
those two vectors and those two vectors
is of the same sign opposite sign as the
orientation of these things okay and
that's something that we discussed on
the exercise sheet many of us did not
get there but you can do this by
comparing the signs of the
determinant
okay are you more or less happy with
this you have not yet um all passed
away
okay let us say a few more things in
preparation for
tomorrow so that we have one night to
sleep over tomorrow morning we'll be
even
smarter the we understand thanks to that
example what those orientations mean
here is a definition then the central
object of the chapter that we
discussing let M be an oriented
manifold
of Dimension say
m and consider a map from M to
M you understood how important this kind
was be a map self map and of course we
are assuming that this map is maybe
differentiable continuous and so
on the left shets
number due to a great
mathematician around middle of the
century called Solomon left
of
f is simply equal to the following
quantity do you know this
letter it's Lambda and it does it's not
a picture for somebody walking but it
does look like
it it's Capital Lambda of f Lambda as in
left set is equal to the intersection
number
of the diagonal with a
graph that's the definition of defit
number why is this number interesting
again look at these stations such as
this if you have the graph of something
and then the diagonal do you remember
which parts of this picture represent a
fixed point the exactly the points where
the graph and the diagonal intersect
those are the fixed points points of
this map which I'd like to remind you in
terms of motivation can then represent
the roots of some equation and so
on so let's just stand by simply
calculating how many intersections there
are how many fixed points there are but
with a sign plus or
minus okay algebraically counting so
that's what let's just number is it's
very easy to um understand now the
theorem which is a extremely important
and extremely easy is the following if
this manifold is closed this oriented
manifold is closed
then the lest number of f is invariant
and the
deformations of F that is is invariant
under
isotopy of the graph
of in gestures say that you have a map
which takes a manifold and then the
something to the manifold okay
transforms the manifold it Maps the
manifold
itself suppose that you have a left
number of this map which represents how
many fixed points there are as I
explained and now let's start deforming
this map maybe you don't like the map
because it's too complicated maybe you
don't like the map because it looks like
Tadashi and you want it to make it look
like very green instead and then you
start deforming the
map yes to something much easier much
more
handsome in the course of theformation
are you going to change the number of
fixed points no you don't because
according to that theorem the V number
is invariant under isotopy but you see
what power this approach has we are
effectively saying if you want to solve
an equation you can deform that equation
to something
simpler provided the deformation is
continuous and then the number of roots
that you get is the same as before so
instead of solving a difficult problem
we can solve an easier problem and then
having solved the easier problem we can
deform back and find the solution to the
original problem does this sound
familiar yes we saw such examples on on
day one last
week this theorem is extremely important
but it's obvious because we know the
intersection the yeah intersection
number is invariant and the isotop is
and Def number is just a special kind of
intersection number so the proof is
obvious from
the central theorem of last chapter
theorem
good I shall go a little over time and
discuss this theorem on an example
always examples examples I don't like
just stating a the I would like to see
it in action let's see how to calculate
a leftest number in practice okay and we
shall take a rest after that example
six what's the
simplest um map of the simplest closed
manifold well you might be tempted say
how about R but you see R is not closed
that's a problem and the intersection
number required for it in variance that
the manifolds be closed you remember
sometimes if you don't have closeness
the intersection Point falls off the
boundary that's bad so the simplest
example is that of a circle not of a
straight line so
rotation of this one dimensional Circle
by let's say angle
Alpha so we have F which takes a an
angle and Ms to theta plus Alpha let's
say but if this result exceeds 2 pi of
course we have to subtract 2 pi so we
are talking about modul 2 pi I hope you
understand what this
means
okay how does that work you have a
circle and you rotating the whole thing
by angle
Alpha
okay this rotation has no fixed Point as
you as you can
see well we have to assume that Alpha is
not the multiple of 2 pi I mean because
if you roted by 2 pi of course
everything is fixed but suppose that
Alpha is not one of 2 pi or 4 Pi or
something like that assume that Alpha is
not a m integer mle 2
pi then this map has no fixed point
right every Point
moves okay well so according to theorem
five the left number for this map which
is still confusing but what should the
lest number of this map
be there are no fix
points some people are very shy
saying tab yeah how about the center of
the ccle I think it is no no no that's a
very good question but it's also if I
may say so a caress question do you
remember from day two
that we spent a lot of time speechifying
about the difference between a circle
and a
dis sphere and a ball when we say a
circle what do we mean we in elementary
terms that people have learned a long
time ago and some uneducated people
continue to use Circle means the
circumference dis means the entire solid
thing including inside so this picture
does not have a
center clear okay
so good I'm happy that somebody asks
such questions every once in a while but
before long we should really get used to
the conceptual distinction between a
circle and a dis sphere and balls
otherwise as you can see even somebody
has clever Asoka and I get perpetually
confused and you know people who don't
make this terminological distinction
continue being confused for the rest of
their lives that's a waste of time well
so what's the lest number it should be
zero because they're no fixed points
let's draw a picture like that although
in this case it's intuitively easy to
understand what's going on but let's
draw the picture nonetheless so this is
the picture of S1 cross S1 or M1 cross
M1 if you like and what's the diagonal
diagonal is going to be denoted in red
it's simply this one that's diagonal of
this
one all right
is that okay and then let's say that
Alpha let's say that this entire length
is 2 pi between 0 and 2 pi yeah so in
fact this point is equal to this point
and this point is equal to this point so
we live not on this square but rather on
the Taurus in
reality here is
Alpha so what is the graph of theta goes
to theta plus Alpha that's easy I hope
it is easy do you know how to draw the
graph of y = x + 1 I hope you can it is
equal
to
this but then what happens when I reach
here well you see this point point 2 pi
is the same point as this so I
reappear here it's a periodic picture
and this point is the same point as this
point okay is that clear because at this
point the x coordinate is 2 pi but it's
the same thing as zero on the circle and
Y component is the same so that's the
picture of GMA of
f how many intersections are there in
this picture between yellow and red no
of course there shouldn't be any so the
um leftest number is
zero you should note what this picture
really is so this picture in fact in
reality lives on S1 cross S1 which is
equal to T2 Sigma 2 if you like so the
real picture looks like this um I'm
going to draw two pictures so let me
draw them a little
smaller here is a picture of a Taurus
seen from
above
of T2 okay can you imagine taus like
this okay what is the graph of the what
is excuse me the
diagonal it starts here let's say um so
let's say that this is one of the s1's
and the other S1 is like
this bless you again I hope you're not
catching code okay that's one s one and
this is
S1
so the graph of Delta
the diagonal looks like this it starts
here and it's a looks like a circle as
see from above and then goes in the back
do you know what this is doing so
imagine the Taurus this is this part of
the car is on this side of Taurus but
then it goes under and it's on the other
side of Taurus comes
back that's the picture
of of the uh
diag
okay what about the picture of the
graph well at this point I'm already a
little higher up I have to rotate this
S1 by a little angle so maybe it's here
and in fact what
this looks like is this kind of
Circle which is slightly shifted I hope
I can draw this
here so that's the graph of gamma and
they don't intersect I hope you can see
this and if you cannot we can try to see
by dancing a dance of some
sort okay that was
easy I'm going to mention yet one more
example and then we'll
finish
that was translation or addition by a
constant angle Alpha let's do
multiplication what happens if we
consider a map which multiplies
angles
next let's fix some number n which is an
integer consider the map another map
which I shall also Den by F which sends
Theta to n * Theta again modul 2
pi yeah and that's again a map from S1
to
S1 what does this map look
like here is what it looks
like take a
circle and this and let's cut the
circle do you see what I have done I
have a circle and I cut it and then you
see this circle that has been cut is now
segment between 0 and 2
pi I have to stretch every Theta to n
Theta which means that I take this
rubber band and then stretch it to n *
size okay Theta goes to n Theta I have
to make it n *
longer so it's going to be a lot of
effort like
this okay and having stretched n times
this n times long
thing I have to then remember that you
see this is 0 to 2 pi this is 0 to 2 pi
this is 0 to 2 pi this is 0 2 pi so 2 pi
4 Pi 6 Pi 8 Pi or something like this
but you see this point 2 pi should be
the same as this point 4 Pi because
we're doing mod mod 2 pi so all I have
to do is to make sure that by the time I
come here I go back so I have to wrap it
around on itself n
times
and stuck
together and then I Squatch the
whole
this is geometrically what the map is
okay so a point somewhere here might be
might be a point here when you stretch
it's a point here but then this is
perhaps 6 Pi * something plus something
but that should be the same point as
this point so I have to sort of wrap it
around and see where this point goes and
the the um final result might be
somewhere here that's the geometry of
this map of uh n times angle what is the
picture that corresponds to this product
and graph and so forth here is what it
is and it's very instructive so I hope
you'll enjoy it the
diagonal is the same as
before um that was in red wasn't
it that's
diagonal I'm sorry this is I should have
drawn it I to do that okay
okay what is the graph of theta goes to
n
Theta you have any
idea what's the graph of y = 4 4X for
example do you have any any
idea of
course it looks like this
right but this point is the same point
as this point so I have to keep going up
with the same slope
and so I have this
picture of
gamma okay so this is zero 2 pi and
that's 2 pi question we have to figure
out number of intersections of Delta and
Gamma how many intersections are there
in this
picture interesting who said three
please identify yourself who said three
I heard three
no nobody said
three one 2 3 you think it's four but in
fact not four but three why because this
point has coordinates 2 pi and 2 pi but
that's the same thing as 0
0 is that clear because we are doing in
a circular fion so that point is the
same thing as this
point in other words was the N minus one
intersections this
point is not
counted
because mod 2
pi it is the
same same
point
as this
point nus one intersection points all
with
s + one why is this because Delta gamma
like that the ambient orientation is
like this so it's positive here it's
positive here it's positive here so plus
one therefore the leftest number of this
map is equal to N - 1
you can see that when n equals um 2
there should be one
intersection when n = three three
intersections when N = - 10 then there
are - 11 intersections what does that
mean that no- 11 that means that there
are 11 intersections but with negative
sign so when I say this plus one it's in
fact not quite right if n is
positive because the slopes are like
this if n is negative slopes are like
this so you get Negative
intersection not zero and zero what if n
is zero you get something like this in
that case Delta here gamma here that's
opposite to the ambient orientation so
zero is in this case and you can see
that when n is zero you get minus one
intersections which is is one
intersection but with a negative
sign okay that's enough I hope that this
somehow clarifies the mechanism by which
we can in practice compute the def
number you can see that the def number
is very easy to Define but somewhat
difficult to compute you have to keep
your cool in order to compute but it's
computable we shall not make many
computations of leftest number this is
probably as hard calculations as as we
shall do this week
okay